Welcome everyone to fall quarter and
welcome to CS 329A.
I hope you made it to the right class.
This class is on self-improving AI
agents.
Anyone
made it to the right class here?
Yes? Okay.
How many of you are here
and doing masters at Stanford?
PhD?
Okay.
A few of you and then undergrad?
Okay. So masters is the big crowd here.
>> There's a good balance. Yeah.
>> It's a really good balance. Uh
So we'll introduce ourselves. So I'm
Akanksha. I have been working in large
language models for a while and I'm an
adjunct professor at Stanford and I'm
also in research
at a startup called Reflection AI.
>> Hi, I'm Azalia Mirhoseini. I'm a I'm an
assistant professor in the CS department
and
Akanksha and I met each other when we
were
at Google Google Brain Google Brain.
Yeah, back in the day and then Google
DeepMind.
And I also worked on Cod and Anthropic
and Gemini at Google
DeepMind and we are so excited to
teach this course again. This is the
second time we're teaching. Of course,
we have made some updates both to the
lectures and also the way we are
kind of conducting everything during the
the for the course.
And we are we were just so amazed by the
amount of interest
for people to join this course. So
we are excited to have you here.
>> The course website is at
cs329a.stanford.edu.
We have updated the website in terms of
all the lecture materials and and the
papers that you'll be reading as well as
what's the homework schedule to expect
the project proposal and project
structures as well.
So, in today's lecture we'll start with
an overview of large language models.
Just how the scaling trends have evolved
over the last 5 years and then we'll
focus more on what we will cover in this
class. And then from there
in the second half of the
this lecture we'll cover the course
logistics and that part you should pay a
lot of attention to because that
influences your grades.
So, let's take a look at an overview of
the trends for large language models.
So, one of the aspects that has been
mind-blowing since GP3 came out is that
there is a
as you scale up the number of parameters
in a model they get better and what this
means is that language models like BERT
and T5 were good but as we increase the
number of parameters they got really
better. They they perform much better
and what this led to is something called
a scaling loss for large language models
which are used in building the base
model for the pre-trained base model
as you increase the amount of compute.
So, there are three graphs here. As you
increase the amount of compute on the
x-axis the loss function on the y-axis
goes down and and the more compute you
have put in the more
the test test loss goes down which leads
to a better model. So, that was one big
aspect that led to GP3 and then all the
subsequent chat GPT, Palm,
Gemini and so on. And then similarly as
you increase the data set size on x-axis
the test loss goes down further on
y-axis. So, that's another aspect of
like another axis of scaling that leads
to better language models. And
the fourth one is of course the third
one is of course parameter count. So, if
you increase the number of layers in a
transformer or the amount of parameters
that are there in the language model
that improves the loss our and that that
leads to a better model. And then this
has been the foundation for a lot of the
this has been the foundation for a long
time until last year where this was
starting to hit some kind of a
saturation point.
So,
from 2018 to almost 2024,
this graph is a little bit outdated but
from 2018 to 2024, the as the model size
has gone up
almost consistently, we have been
increasing the the size of the model.
So, we started with something like BERT
was 340 million parameters, GPT-2 was
1.5 billion parameters, and then GPT-3
was 175 billion parameters, and then
PaLM was 540 billion, and then
there was a bunch of subsequent models,
and GPT-4 is estimated to be
there which is like trillions of
parameters. So, you can imagine that
there has been an exponential growth in
just the model size of for large
language models. The large stands for
that they're growing in size, and that
has been one of the key areas in which
the models have been getting better.
So, why do we care about the models
getting bigger? What does this lead to?
So, as I was explaining that as the
models get bigger, they continuously
improve in performance on natural
language benchmarks, on various other
benchmarks, reasoning benchmarks, and so
on.
And then other interesting aspect that I
will show you in a moment is that they
learn how to do few-shot learning. So,
earlier you have to fine-tune the model
for a specific domain, but just by
giving a few examples, the model can
follow that template and and reason in
that same vein which makes it extremely
easy to prototype things. And then the
third aspect is that as the models
become bigger, they have emergent
behavior where the capabilities like
reasoning only emerge in larger models.
So, just to understand few-shot learning
or zero-shot learning here. So,
if if the model is given a question like
or a task like translate English to
French,
it's able to give So this is called a
prompt. Like it's given a task translate
English to French and then it's asked to
translate cheese to whatever is the
French word. If the model can predict
the answer without
actually being trained on the specific
task, then that would be called
zero-shot learning. And then few-shot
learning,
in addition to giving the
description of the task, you're also
giving a few examples. So in this
particular case, it's given translate
English to French and it's given a few
examples of the translation from English
to French and then it's asked to
translate cheese and it's able to
translate that and you can see that this
capability shows up in the large
language models across a large number of
tasks and that has been one of the key
areas that GPT-3 and Palm and other
models enabled and then that
subsequent innovations came from
reasoning aspects of this.
So on the reasoning side,
as models have become bigger, they have
this emergent behavior of reasoning
which Azalia will tell us a little bit
more about.
>> So as the models become bigger, not only
we have this kind of a predictive
scaling laws property that we kind of
know how the loss function's going to go
down as we throw in more compute data
and parameters in the model, there are
new kind of behaviors that appear in the
model that they didn't have before and
we never could predict that until we had
these bigger models and saw these kind
of behavior in them. And one of the most
important
one of those behaviors is the emergent
is the chain of thought behavior. And
for those of you who are not familiar
with this, here is how it works. So in a
usual prompt prompting of a model, we
can ask a model in this case a
a math problem
and then we can give it a one-shot
example. Here is a math problem, here is
the answer. Now I ask you a similar but
not exact and not exactly the same math
problem, and the model is expected to
answer that.
Um
And the model might be able to use the
the one-shot example or it might not be.
But we can do better here by not only
give an example in but also provide the
reasoning or the chain of thought on how
we got to that answer. So, in this case,
the question is a very simple question.
Roger has five tennis balls. He buys two
more cans of tennis balls. Each can Each
can has three tennis balls. How many How
many total tennis balls does he have
now? And instead of just saying 11, like
we're walking the model through how to
get to this.
Um Roger started with five balls. Two
cans of three tennis balls is six. And
uh 5 + 6 is 11.
Uh And with this example, then the model
has become familiar with the process to
get to the answer, and it can leverage
that to answer new problems.
Well, obviously this is a very simple
problem. Any like one-B parameter model
nowadays can solve this. Doesn't need a
an example or a few shot or a chain of
thought. But the chain of thought
property itself is a property that is
holding to this day and it's a very very
important property for the reasoning
models and all the thinking models and
all the prog and many much of the
progress that we have seen um
in the past year or so.
Now, um
this property again appears as we have
larger and larger models. Here are three
models, Lambda, GPT, and PaLM. And as
you can see, the chain of thought and
this is some results on the math some
math data set. And these models
when they're smaller, like eight billion
parameter for Lambda or
um deep for GPT around 7 billion. They
can't really benefit from chain of
thought. Like it doesn't do anything for
them. But as they become larger
or for a palm model again at 8 billion,
it can leverage this chain of thought
property and learn from the reasoning
that is and the the process that is
provided in the context in order to
solve problems better.
And not only that, there are other kind
of abilities to solve new task as we
increase the size of the models. Like
for example, small models can all of a
sudden solve mod arithmetics better or
solve
word unscramble problem just by having
this larger size and this property. You
see that all of a sudden it appears at a
certain size.
And because of all of this, we still
as in frontier companies and labs are
still interested in pushing the the the
scaling laws and not only get the
natural kind of progression, but also we
are we we will see more and more of
these kind of emergent behavior that we
are
that is going to be very important.
Now, a little bit of history here. So
chat GPT was launched in
November 2022.
Obviously, it was one of the most
successful
kind of
apps or software ever created. The time
to reach 1 million users for it was
5 days, which is significantly
faster than any that many of the other
famous
software that you can see there or
services that you can see there. And
there were pieces of
kind of innovation on top of just
scaling up the parameter size of the
model that were very important to make
chat GPT what it was and to make that
kind of leapfrog and over the previous
models like GPT-3 and so on. And two two
important piece here but were
um the instruction tuning and um the
reinforcement learning from human
feedback which which we're going to
briefly mention in the next slides but
throughout this course we're going to
learn more and more about them. Um so
let's
first and then um we're going to learn
about all of these in more details but
let's just take a step back and see how
the process works. So the pre-training
step is
the step that
the the beginning of any language model
training.
Uh that's the easiest step and we just
train the model to predict the next
token out of all sort of text and data
and so on.
And then this is the fine-tuning step
that was a key differentiating factor
for a model like chat GPT. Um and let's
start with um
uh the first aspect of fine fine-tuning
which is kind of alignment between human
preferences.
So when a model is pre-trained it has no
sense it has seen all data on the
internet on the in the books everywhere
but it has no sense of like what is
right and wrong and what is it just have
it this statistically knows about the
state of the world but does it it
doesn't exactly know things or know how
to follow instructions. So the next step
in training these models
uh is the the the the [clears throat]
step where we try to steer the AI models
to follow the goals and preferences uh
and values of humans. Um
and this is still a big problem it's a
big issue we we haven't like mastered it
yet but as the models become as we
progress models are becoming better and
much more uh kind of like
uh
powerful in the things that they can do.
So, it turns out that we can fine-tune
the models to be aligned. For example,
here are some graphs that show what if
we take our base base model that's just
pre-trained and fine-tune it for things
like sensibleness or safety. And
these are like these are data that that
we have collected. High-quality data for
kind of showing the model what it what
we mean by what's safe and what's unsafe
or what's sensible and what doesn't make
sense. And these are like more curated
like more highly curated data that we
pass to the model for fine-tuning and to
make the model more aligned with the
values or the or the preferences of
humans.
Um
So,
going back, let's just walk through this
process again. So,
the first stop when we take a
pre-trained language model is
fine-tuning with next token prediction,
which follows the same process as
pre-training, but this time on data that
is much more higher quality.
For example, this could be data from
books, creative essays,
data that companies pay a whole lot
millions of dollars or hundreds of
millions of dollars potentially to buy
this data that's really high quality,
and then we train the we fine-tune the
model on those. And the model becomes
much better as a result of that.
Um
The The next step is instruction tuning.
And by instruction tuning, what we mean
is that we show the model again
traditionally in the past 2 years, this
instruction tuning data is like a
combination of human generated data or
templates and then and then and the
synthetic data. But, the way this
instruction to fine-tuning works is that
we do have
instruction and then question answer
pairs
where the model learns how to follow the
questions and answers them. For example,
here an instruction for
tuning data set could be about the
weather like please answer the following
question. What is the boiling point of
nitrogen? And then that this is the
answer.
Or, we can have chain of thought
fine-tuning where we
show the model how it can walk through a
process to get to the answer. And then
we have the label, we have the results
over here. And this is like these pairs
of like questions and instructions and
answers. And again, this this data set
is very um is
is there's a lot of effort that goes
into this data set and the quality of
data set and the uh generality of it uh
has a lot of impact on the quality of
the model that we get at this stage.
Um and after this point in the model
becomes more and more like um
like the models we see today. Like you
can ask them questions, you can go back
and forth with them. They they have this
sense of like how to uh perceive a
question and how to walk through kind of
uh some sort of like process to get to
to an answer.
And the next step after instruction
fine-tuning is this process of
um using human preferences
and fine-tuning the model based on that.
And this process is called RLHF or
reinforce reinforcement learning from
human feedback. Um the way this is
different from the previous system is
the way we create the objective function
and uh create the data. So, in this
case, instead of like just creating some
supervised prompt and labels, we are
basically creating a reward model out of
human preferences. So, companies spend a
lot of money
uh
asking humans, sometimes experts,
sometimes just
humans, normal humans, uh about
questions and the answers generated by
the model. And we ask the the humans to
rate them
to see which one is correct and is not
correct. And that's how we can create
some sort of a reward model here.
Um and this reward model is instead
instead of human, then we can use the
reward model in order to kind of like
guide the parameters of our LLM towards
uh generating answers that are in line
with this reward model. So, basically,
we want the the generations by the model
uh to be such that this reward model
says, "Yes, these are good generations."
Um we're going to learn more about this
here, but I wanted We wanted to you to
have um the high-level idea of what
RLAIF means. Uh and we can collect We
can have different reward type different
types of reward. For example, we could
ask the model to reward a pair of
answers based on their correctness or
helpfulness or specificity or
harmlessness, all sort of reward
functions that we can define. And
depending on how we want the models to
be and what we care most about, we can
weight these different reward models and
kind of use that in the RLAIF process.
So, these step at a at a high level, of
course, there's a lot of effort goes
into that, but like pre-training and
then
um
fine-tuning on higher-quality data,
instruction tuning, and RLAIF are were
the core kind of components that made um
a model like ChatGPT over over something
that existed over all the large models
um
like GPT-3 and prior models. So, that
made the huge difference in how good and
capable the models were.
Um
Uh
so
so that was very cool up until last year
or a year a year year and a half ago,
pre-training and then fine-tuning were
the big pieces.
Uh but since a year and a half ago, it
turns out inference is also a frontier
for making the models much more capable.
Um
so
and that
opened like a whole set of whole lot of
new research and directions and ways
that we can make the model better.
Um so let's think let's talk about it a
little bit. Like this is a work we did
in my lab last year
uh last summer. It it was called large
language monkeys. Um
and it's kind of inspired by the
infinite monkey theorem and it's related
to inference scaling. Um
how many of you have heard of the
infinite monkey theorem?
Okay, that's a good amount. So, the idea
of the infinite monkey theorem uh what
it says is that
it's not proven, but what it says is
that if you have a monkey and a kind of
a typing machine and then we keep
letting the monkey type all day forever,
um after some time you will have the
works of William Shakespeare in in the
things that the monkey types.
Um
so we were inspired by that to name our
project. Uh but the idea here was that
let's let's have the LLM be the monkey
and uh let's
uh ask the model over and over again to
solve a given input problem.
Uh you can think of it as parallel
sampling or parallel generation. So,
instead of asking the model once to
solve the input problem, you can ask it
many times. And also, let's assume you
have some sort of a verifier or
selection mechanism, so you can pick
which one of these generated responses
were correct.
Um and then you output that in your
system. That becomes the out the final
output. So, the model, instead of
generating one answer, generates many,
many answers. And then your verifier
selects which one of them is correct and
then outputs one of the correct ones. Um
you can think of a verifier as, say,
some unit tests. If the problem is a
generating code, the verifier can could
be the unit test that we run against the
code and we see which which one of the
code generations passes all the unit
tests and so on.
Um The reason this is very This is a a
This can be a possible possibility here
is that models are um do not are not uh
there is some variance in the data the
models generate responses. It's not
deterministic. And you can even control
the variation in the model responses
with this thing called temperature. So,
you can force the model or encourage the
model to generate more different
responses as you ask a question.
Um
And here, now let's see some of the
results of this repeated sampling. For a
bunch of tasks like math and coding
benchmarks, we increased the number of
samples per problem from one, this is
the normal one,
uh to 10,000.
And here we are showing the coverage or
the fraction of problems that are solved
by at least one of these samples.
And what we are seeing here is that um
so the red line, the red dashed one, was
the GPT-40
model. And while these blue and green
lines, which were the llama 8B, llama 3
8B, and 7B, were worse than GPT for our
model with one sample, but if we
increase the number of samples from
these models, in all of these cases,
they do better than the GPT 4 model.
And what it says is that it kind of
seems like the model or models already
know a whole lot more
than what you get out of them when you
just ask them once, right? So, this is
the kind of the underlying property of
inference scaling because it seems like
we can get a whole lot of a whole lot
more capability and problem-solving kind
of ability from these models if we just
bring in this inference scaling. Here,
you're showing repeated sampling, but
there are many other ways to do that.
And we are So, the reason it's called
inference scaling is that we're not
touching any of the parameters of the
model. The model is fixed, and we are
just like at inference time, we are
creating different ways to generate to
kind of produce generations from the
model and use them to generate
higher-quality answers or answers to
harder problems for the model. Um
the interesting part here is that for
some of these problems, out of these
10,000 solutions, maybe like three or
four of them were correct for a single
problem. So, it shows that how how kind
of
um
uh how important it is to to scale the
inference to really get to the
core capability of the models.
Sorry, what's the question?
>> What is the difference of GPT-3 and when
we select traversing all the possible
answers and we do
and select and select all the
>> So, the possible answers need to be
generated somehow by the model, right?
So, so this is like the space of all
possible answers to the model is way
bigger, like like right? We can like if
we do like a tree search or a random
search, it's like way bigger, right?
There's no way to like hit even like
imagine like we are asking a human like
just sit down and solve this problem,
right? There is a limit to
Um of course there is no limit to human
creativity, human's creativity, but
there is a limit to how many generations
we can have, right? Or if you're
randomizing, there's a whole lot set of
answers that can be generated and it's
and this is like highly still highly
sample efficient, right? 10,000 is not a
whole lot, especially like for example
for the math um F2F,
some of these problems are really hard
like IMO level problems. Like these are
really hard problems that a tiny model
like a 7 and a Llama 8B can solve.
>> How does it compare how how does the
latency compare with
like when you do actually generate all
the samples like compared to the GPT-3
or all, right? Like how does the latency
>> Yeah, of course there is a trade-off um
and we we have we touch on that in the
in the lecture that I go more details
toward this. The parallel samples, the
good thing about them that they're they
can be running parallel.
Um so, from a latency perspective,
that's less of an issue, but of course
there is the frontier of cost trade-offs
between how much compute you're spending
and and we will look into that. And it
varies, it varies depending on the type
of and complexity of the problems.
Yes.
>> The latency when you have
a pair viable depending
Yeah.
Yes, great question again. It's a very
hard When you have verifiers, it's much
easier. When you don't have verifiers,
there's this whole set of research on
how to train LLMs judge or LLMs reward
functions or LLMs with tools becoming
and we're going to learn about all of
it. We have a lecture just dedicated to
verifiers, so.
Yeah.
No,
yeah, we can't like have the temperature
being too high because it's just it's
going to be gibberish, like the model
doesn't generate. So, we
There's actually like a research project
last year was like on tuning that or
like figuring out what temperature.
Usually, if you go beyond like 1.2 or
so, it's
it's not great, yeah.
Yeah.
But there are there are other tricks
that you can do to
kind of kind of uh
make the model be more um
like have more diversity in the type of
answers
and that can be useful.
Uh
All right.
Um
So,
let's look at this. So, now, again,
going back to the events of last year,
year and a half, um we had the DeepSeek
model. I think it came out in
>> December.
>> DeepSeek came out December 2024.
Uh oh, well.
>> It's been out for a
>> Short time or long time, I don't know.
The both. Uh so, so then models like
DeepSeek came last year. So, basically,
a core kind of innovation in Deep Seek
and then the 01 series Gemini thinking
and such were that. Now, we are kind of
bringing this fine-tuning and test time
scaling together because with this test
time scaling and the models themselves,
we have this new like kind of engine
that we can generate a whole lot of
synthetic data um
for for example, for problems like for
math problems where we know the answer,
we can have the model generate different
like kind of answers that leads to that
final final kind of golden answer. Or
for the coding problems, we can use the
model to generate tons of data during
test time scaling,
uh tons of like quality data to solve
coding problems, and that becomes part
of our training set now. We can use that
to fine-tune the model
to to become better. So, that kind of
bringing these two together became a big
piece in thinking models and reasoning
models. Um and this this is like a This
is like a an area that is like really
really important. There's just so much
to be explored in this because again,
there there is no It's kind of
open-ended, right? There's no boundary
in how good the models can become with
test time scaling and then bringing that
back to the process of training the
model or fine-tuning the model to become
better is very exciting, and that's kind
of the self-improving piece that we are
very excited about.
Um so, a little bit about reasoning
models. Um
in the language monkeys, what we were
showing was the coverage. Like if we had
access to a verifiers, how uh we we can
see the kind of a log linear kind of
scaling laws with the number of samples.
Um
and all OpenAI, when they released 01
last September, um they showed a a log
linear relationship this time with pass
at one for these like hard hard Amy uh
benchmark which is like I said a really
difficult uh math questions. So, as
they're show what they're showing here
is that as they're increasing test time
compute and this is in log scale
um
uh the the accuracy the pass at one
accuracy of the model goes up and this
is for test time alone. Uh previously
uh it this has been shown for training
but it's very interesting that this kind
of scaling applies to test time as well
um without changing the parameter count
of the model. Um
Um I'm going to walk you through like
one a few examples of how this kind of
reasoning or test time uh scaling
uh kind of is
works with models like O3 and or Gemini.
So, one motivation here is that for
difficult problems just like humans
think a lot more, spend a lot more time,
or consider many different strategies,
uh thinking models do the same and they
may use a chain of thought or other
techniques to just go go about like
solving a problem um
and
there are different steps to that. For
example, um problem analysis is one step
like the model first sees a problem and
tries to analyze it. Um then it can do
the task decomposition breaking a task
into kind of simpler tasks that are more
addressable. Um then there is the self
uh evolution strategies where the model
kind of try something, sees the
feedback, for example runs some
tests on the code or use a uses a
calculator or just judges the answer and
it can use that feedback to optimize
itself. Um there's self-correction and
there are alternative proposals if
something doesn't work, the model can
backtrack and kind of, um,
try different approach. These are some
key principle principles that the model,
uh, probably at some point, uh, pieces
of it were trained as part of the
training kind of data set were curated
by humans, but a big part of it is also
the model kind of acquiring these skills
during this fine-tuning process and RL
like RL from synthetic data process that
the model does. Um, here is an example
of like how O 1 does analysis. Um,
uh, the model is asked to write a bash
script, um,
uh, that takes a matrix and then
outputs, uh, the transpose of the that
matrix. The model starts with just like
humans, like starts like thinking, what
are the pieces important pieces here?
So, the user is requesting a bash
script, um, let's understand the input
and output, uh, formats of this matrix,
um,
and and so on. So, the model just thinks
itself,
um, and amazingly this kind of like
it's like a progression of chain of
thought. This is like helping the model
finding the answer, but the difference
between chain of thought and this is
that the model itself is
producing this chain of thought.
Um, there's of course task
decomposition, like in this case for the
the approach, uh,
the model thinks about parsing the
input, building the matrix as an array
of, uh, as as an array of arrays, and so
on. Um,
there's also self-correction, which is a
big important piece of, um,
this is is an important piece here, and
I don't know how many of you have seen
that when trying with the models that
you can see the thinking traces. Uh, and
this is actually pretty common, like the
model starts something and then in the
middle says, "Wait, the correct for like
there's something wrong, maybe. Um, or
and maybe I need to fix that." And it's
very, very cool that the model can do
that itself. Um, so reasoning models
when they came out, like models like 01,
compared to a model like GPT-4o,
which model, um, they tend to be better
in, obviously, the reasoning task. For
example, in math calculation, data
analysis, programming and such, they all
kind of outperform GPT-4o, but not
necessarily in personal writing or
editing text and so on.
Yeah. Question?
>> Do you think the gains due to this
asking for a reasoning process due to
actually the act of generating this
reasoning process or just the act of
asking the model to think or to use the
composition at all? Like, for example,
if you
think step-by-step but don't generate
out loud,
like don't actually generate those
thought processes which are there but
without saying
>> Yeah.
Um,
I repeat the question. Like, do you
you're saying that is it the Do you
think the reasoning models are becoming
what they are is based on the Is it
based on the loud way of thinking?
>> I I think the question is that Is it
because of the, um, reasoning process or
is it because of things step-by-step?
The chain of thought.
Like, is it the data thinking difference
or is it the the instruction? Um,
>> It's I mean, so the data basically has
made the model kind of become a
generalized thinker, right?
Like, the model can and the all of it
All of these steps, like breaking down
the problem, being able to backtrack,
being being able to do analysis, all of
these are these skills that the model
has learned during this thinking
optimization process that now generalize
to other things and they're helping the
model right now.
>> So, I think the other way to look at it
is as Ali presented repeated sampling.
So, if you had just a base model right
after pre-training, it would be able to
do some reasoning.
But, at the same time it will generate
different kinds of reasoning chains and
it doesn't quite know which one is
correct. So, a lot of the
what we will cover in train time or test
time scaling really comes down to it
learns which is correct. So, pass at one
accuracy goes up which is what you were
seeing in the reasoning models as
opposed to like pass at K or coverage
which is what you were seeing in the
repeated sampling results.
>> Yeah. And and one other way to think
about like yes, these kind of like kind
of
deep thinking and things that the model
generates is actually helping the model
every time to solve a new problem.
Um
and although it's like very expensive
for the model to generate those things,
still like we want them to generate
those because it
leads to better answers.
Um
Any other questions? Yes.
>> Do you use a different model for the
reasoning stuff versus generating the
final answer? Like maybe a smaller or
like a probabilistic one just for the
reasoning and the final answer is the
large model.
>> Um
So, typically the reasoning capabilities
have gone up with the model size. So, if
if anything uh you would use the larger
model for reasoning traces and then
maybe you collect a bunch of reasoning
traces and then have a smaller model
summarize the answer.
>> Yeah. So, the models like this is like
at least currently, things may change,
they like their own traces more. Even if
they're the traces are coming from a
better model, they tend to like their
traces their own generated traces more.
And we're going to have talk about
swirl, this is one of the papers that uh
>> the multi-step reasoning
>> the multi-step reasoning that we talked
about. What if we bring a different
model, not in the context of generating
reason traces, but in in the context of
like evaluating and giving feedback. And
we we're going to see that as well. But
models, surprisingly or not
surprisingly, like their own traces a
lot more.
>> For reasoning models, how are they
taught to reason? Is it a hardcoded set
of sequences of or taught to do traces
or they somehow fine-tuned to say, "You
need to do this much or this kind of
thing that will cause the traces to
generate."
>> So, I don't think there's a published
piece of work that really covers this
bit. Uh
>> It's both, yeah.
>> But it's it's a bit of both. At the same
time, the base model did have the
thinking capability to begin with,
right? It would go do in some go do some
amount of thinking. One thing that we
will cover in the classes this notion of
outcome rewards model and process reward
model and how you can use that feedback
to get the model back.
>> Yeah, there's always some bootstrapping.
Like, okay, here are different ways.
Like, chain of thought itself, which is
heavily used in the instruction tuning
of data set,
tell shows the model some ways of like
how to think.
And there could be like some templates
showing
for the model fine-tuning. But
the things that the model, if you just
ask them any ask it any question and it
comes up with that, there's a whole lot
of generalization that. So, models have
gone way above like what the data or
instructions that are used for training
them.
Yes.
>> Uh can you repeat some of Is there a way
to make the number of samples dependent
on the problem
>> Please speak up.
>> The number of samples, can they be
dependent on problem difficulty?
>> I don't think there's a published piece
of work that does that. Uh but
yeah,
>> we just So,
So, when So, there is
follow-up work to that where we you use
a reward model and then you can use
that. So, assuming the reward model has
some notion of complexity, if you
haven't solved it, it can guide like
more sampling or whether it's repeated
or parallel.
Uh but that's definitely an interesting
direction to explore.
Yeah.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, we need to get to the Oh, we
haven't. Right.
>> Yeah, let me cover these.
>> Okay, so we you now know about large
language models and then you heard about
how they learned how to think and then
they learned how to reason.
So, what's next and why does this Why is
this course relevant? So, a lot of what
this course is about is that large
language models as chatbots or as
reasoning models are basically still
single turn like or or just like in the
chat format. So, they're not
accomplishing a task for you. They're
fun to interact with, but they're not
necessarily accomplishing a task for
you. What has happened this year
almost in the last few months and it's
been surprising is that
agents like Claude Code or Deep Research
have really enabled people to do
real-world workflows.
So, they're agentic workflows which can
achieve tasks that you ask them to do
end-to-end. So, for example, if you want
to go research and figure out where
should I
rent a home perhaps for the entire year
for if I want to take a class at
Stanford.
The model would actually be able to do a
whole bunch of analysis and like go look
at a lot of different websites and
actually summarize the results and give
you pros and cons of different places.
This used to not be possible before. So,
this
will cover a little bit of how that that
becomes possible and how this course
allows you to learn about that. And then
Claude Code for example, any of you are
Codex which is the coding agent from
OpenAI, if you're using that, what you
will see is that just by giving
instructions in English, you can modify
files or you can like figure out test
cases and and whatnot. So, it really
uh is become a coding productivity tool
in in the day-to-day workflows for
software engineers at this point in
time.
So, what what is the transition from LLM
to agents? So, as I was giving you the
example of Deep Research and of uh
coding agents, basically the goal
basically now the uh model can be given
a goal and it will plan out the steps,
then it will go interact with uh the
environment, and based on the feedback,
it will correct its steps until it
achieves the goals or it will come back
and say, "I cannot achieve the goal."
So, this notion of like having some
notion of a goal, uh taking actions
towards that goal, getting the feedback,
and then deciding when to stop, that's
what makes agents uh different from the
chatbot times of what you were doing
before. And um
this also might require interacting with
tools uh which are external to what the
model itself is doing, getting some
inputs from there, but it still stays on
track of like whatever task it's uh
choosing to accomplish, which might mean
that it has to have some form of memory
to keep track of the task that it's
trying to accomplish.
So, what has been uh accomplished? So,
like in in in several cases in simpler
cases, you can achieve these uh um
these end-to-end goals like Deep
Research can like be accomplished
end-to-end. But, in most scenarios,
you're still having very static
workflows. So, today what exists is
closer to agentic workflows where you
have um some sort of an input where
you're giving a model the goal and then
uh
what this slide is showing you is that
one model is perhaps uh giving the
output like a solution and then another
model is judging it and then deciding
based on that whether the solution
should be accepted. So, that's like one
orchestration framework that's possible.
Uh Deep Research will be more of the
second one where you're basically
generating
you're calling the LLM on multiple
possible inputs and then aggregating
these
things to get the output which will be a
summary of the deep research results.
So, this is a very
cartoonish abstraction of what agentic
workflows might look like and you can
generalize from there, but instead of
having like very open-ended loop that I
was showing you here where you're
supposed to go take an action from the
environment and come back and do some
feedback.
Um,
it's easier for open-ended problems to
like construct this graph by hand of
like how a human would do it and then
like get this feedback perhaps from an
LLM which is the LLM evaluator here. So,
a lot of the real world workflows still
have this paradigm, but in in certain
cases we are starting to see signs of
life for what's possible in this slide
encoding being one and research being
another one.
So, typically the workflows will have
things like LLM calls. So, you would
basically call an LLM with an
instruction or some form of like input
and then you're asking the LLM to give
you an output. It will have some form of
verifiers. We'll cover verifiers in a
whole lecture by itself. It will have
some form of critics or judges which is
effectively LLM as a judge paradigm.
There might be tool calls. For example,
for deep research you have to actually
go search the web to figure out what
exactly is the content that you should
be looking at. So, there might be tool
calls of that form or
getting some value around
what exactly is the weather.
Um,
and similarly search would be another
tool call. And then you would
orchestrate these in in some form of a
workflow. So, a simplest workflow here
would be prompt chaining. So, similar to
reasoning models where the task gets
decomposed into subtasks, prompt
chaining would simply be like you have
chained a bunch of different subtasks
that you're supposed to go accomplish to
achieve the end-to-end goal. There might
be routing. Routing works for complex
tasks where you say, "Okay, if this is
very complex, then go do this more
complicated set of LLM calls, and if
it's less complicated, then do this
simpler workflow."
Um there might be parallelization where
you like deep research is one example
where you you can have multiple LLM
calls work simultaneously on researching
different keywords that you give it as
input to the LLM, and then uh finally
you aggregate the output, or you might
break the task into independent
subtasks, and then uh combine uh the
solution. Or you might have this notion
of orchestrator where you basically are
actually using some sort of a
In simple words, LLM managers where
central LLM is actually doing the
planning. So, in Claude code, you
actually start to see that that there is
some notion of like a plan that it comes
up with, and then based on that plan, it
will like make subsequent LLM calls.
You might have an evaluator or a judge.
So, instead of like getting feedback
from real-world like user or from some
sort of a actual running a unit test, it
actually might just use LLM as a judge,
and we will have uh some homeworks that
will cover this aspect. And then you
might have verifiers. Verifiers are
things where you can actually verify the
output. So, in code for example, if you
run the code, how do you know that this
code is correct? So, typically as
software developers, we write unit
tests. Uh so, similarly, verifiers might
be running some kind of unit test to
check whether what LLM generated is
correct. And in domains which are
verifiable, uh math, code, um and other
domains that are more rule-based, uh
this verification is a good way to give
feedback back to the model so that um it
can correct its steps.
So, most of these uh
workflows mean that the
uh the LLM needs to be better at
planning. It needs to be better at
multi-step reasoning, and it needs to be
better at self-improvement. Like when it
makes mistakes, it needs to be able to
correct itself. So, effectively, these
are sort of new paradigms that the
current set of LLMs just with reasoning
were not quite accomplishing, and these
are some of the topics we do plan to
cover in subsequent lectures.
And just to drive the point home around
coding agents, so this is a very simple
example. This is actually
I should have updated the slide to four
cloud code, but basically, what this is
showing is that you have an LM agent,
and
it's interacting with the computer
these days just with the terminal. You
give it an instruction where you might
tell it that you want to implement a
task,
and then
has some navigation of repository,
searching of files, all of these tool
calls around like viewing files, editing
lines, and then it will go execute a
bunch of commands in the terminal, and
based on the output, it might be like,
"Okay, I need to go edit this other
file, or I need to go look at this other
file." So, if you look at this loop,
this very much mirrors uh
what was So, this was not quite reliable
last year, and it's just starting to get
reliable in what we're seeing in the
realm of coding agents now.
Yes.
I mean, I think the paradigm is very
much the same. It's it's mostly a matter
of more powerful models, and then better
RL.
RL with verifiable rewards is working.
The train time scaling is working well.
I mean, it's computer data, right? One
of those two, but like just also, once
the models start to get better, there's
the self-improvement loop that kicks in.
Uh because you can now generate tasks,
and the tasks become more reliable. So,
in the published pieces of work, if you
look at say Code Monkeys, which we coded
last year,
if you can generate unit tests
for whatever code the model generated
and then see if the
generated unit tests are
making things better, then that that
that's a very good way to verify things,
right?
>> Yeah, like model-based. It seems like to
some extent, if we have good verifiers,
um
we can make the model generate the the
right code.
Um but the question is how do we do
that? And there are ways to do it. And
we
we would be happy to
for you guys to take research projects
in that domain, too. But obviously, it's
an active research area, but there are
ways to make improvements that we can
discuss.
>> what you're alluding to is this notion
of generator-verifier gap. So, it's easy
for models to generate a whole bunch of
nonsense or sensible set of like
reasoning traces or like useful set of
content. But at the end of the day,
whether that's useful or not, we need
feedback loop for that. And if you're
creative writing, how much feedback can
you get? So, human feedback ends up
becoming a bottleneck. In domains where
you can have good feedback, that's where
it's possible to continue to improve the
model. And that like but where getting
robust verification, a lot of robust
verification is hard. So, uh Azalia will
cover a paper that she did in her her
lab about like how to combine verifiers.
And but what verification continues to
be one of the bottlenecks in this space
to make them better.
>> Yes.
>> Um just like intuitively, like in
pre-training, you get
abilities to find looking at the same
logical abilities.
>> Mhm.
>> So, just like to me, intuitively, I'm
trying to figure out why there's a
significant drop.
>> Mhm.
>> Because like we're sort of dividing up
what they know.
>> Mhm.
>> And we have logical abilities that I
guess shouldn't exist
>> Mhm.
>> in pre-training.
>> Um
So, yeah, I I guess like I'm I'm not
completely resonating with like
>> I I think this is still an active area
of research. So, there is different set
of opinions around what really improves
the model. Is it RL or is it like the
the pre-training diverse data by itself?
And I I don't think there's single point
of consensus at this point in time. Both
processes help. Um what you just said,
uh which I'll repeat for the class, is
that if pre-training is the place where
uh the model after repeated sampling
should be able to at least have one
solution correct out of if it was
generating a large number of samples,
then uh this notion of giving feedback
should improve the pass at one accuracy,
but should not improve the model. Why is
it like such a big jump? But I think um
that whole loop is not completely well
understood. It's like the first signs of
life and it starts to get
commercialized, but I think there's a
lot more research still open in this
area.
So, that's only one uh way of thinking
about it. There are other um at least
some signs of life that say that you can
continue to do RL and then that will
continue to improve the model. Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
So, uh so this is basically covering a
lot of the same set of points, but uh
one abstraction that is worth taking
away from this particular chart is that
even when you give the model a goal, it
has to clarify the user intent. So, it's
like not always obvious to it what the
user wants. And then it might go search
for relevant files and then whatever um
set of uh actions it chooses to take,
often times it needs some form of
verification. In this particular case,
it's based on um
passing the tests and it might actually
generate the tests that needs to pass,
which um
which is also uh mentioned here. But the
the key idea is that
if you give it a task, how does it come
back and how do you know that it's going
to complete what you asked it for? Often
times the users will not specify the
problem well enough. So, asking
clarifying the user intent so that it
knows what to go look for and how to
verify it starts to become important and
in models like 03, I think they have
seen a lot of these traces end to end.
So, they are able to like do the
planning, the reasoning, the multi-step
reasoning and like come back with the
conclusion, but
a lot of this is needed for um
completing tasks end to end or having an
end to end goal.
And where this has been super useful is
if you have repeated repetitive tasks
like code migrations or version upgrades
or if you need to restructure the code
base.
Or if you have tasks that involve data
engineering where you have to basically
do some sort of extract the data and
then do some sort of clean clean up on
the data or if you have to do some sort
[snorts] of data warehouse migration.
So, a lot of this work tends to be
extremely
repetitive and it's much easier to just
delegate it to coding agents.
Same for unit tasks often times like
much easier to like start to give it to
coding agents.
Another area where agents have become
extremely prevalent is in customer
support. It's one of the most thankless
jobs that
when when you are on the customer
support side of things you have to do
and using LLMs to do that definitely
makes
streamlines the experience in
interesting ways. So, one simple set of
examples ends up being like you can use
them to do live transcriptions. So, that
gives you a very nice record and and
you're seeing that even for meetings
these days.
Another simple example is that you can
have knowledge assist. So, if you have a
database of information, the customer
support agent does not need to know
everything. They can consult with the
LLM and and get an answer and surface
the relevant article which is better
than having just search
like an index and search by itself.
Smart replies. So, in in chat often
times this has existed for a while, but
you can use an agent to like give chat
responses and then having a call summary
can help you um
you can use the call summary to really
improve the customer experience by
itself as well. So, overall, I think in
the customer support area, there are
[snorts] multiple companies that are
going after this area, but uh
there are different segments of the
problem that can be addressed using LLMs
and they have been super useful and then
there's also the end-to-end stuff that's
starting to happen here.
And then the third example that we will
use and actually some of the homeworks
is that if you have very complex topics
and you want to provide a comprehensive
report, um
earlier it used to be that you had to do
a literature review and then you had to
summarize each paper and then you had to
synthesize these things and these days
you can just give it to an LLM and
actually do it for you and um study
maybe more articles than you would. So,
typically, if you give it an example
like uh say 2022 Winter Olympics opening
ceremony, it will identify what
references to go look at, then it will
construct an outline of like, okay,
these references are relevant or not,
and then summarize each references as to
what is the relevant content and then
combine them to create a full-length
article, um which is
uh very impressive in certain cases and
and you'll get to try it in one of the
homeworks.
And then even uh more uh forward-looking
um these research agents are starting to
be used for uh as AI scientists. So,
basically, they're starting to assist
scientists in say uh solving math
problems or solving science problems.
So, here the LLM is used as a
brainstorming thing to come up with
ideas to the idea generation phase, then
the experiment iteration phase, it might
actually help you iterate on the
experiments that you are hoping to work
on. This is from the AI scientist paper.
And then in the paper write-up phase, it
will help you improve uh
the the paper write-up by itself.
And what's interesting uh is that
even even though these models
hallucinate just I just the notion that
they can come up with so many different
set of ideas
as an AI scientist it might actually
brainstorm or like give you ideas
outside what you would have thought if
you had just like taken a bunch of
courses or or if you're a researcher and
you've been in the field for a long time
sometimes the reading the web allows
these LLMs to come up with ideas that
are way outside the box and can be a
very good brainstorming um
way uh so these have been super useful
for in the AI [clears throat] scientist
style of work.
Okay, so
let's move to course logistics but
before that do we have any questions?
Yes.
>> To clarify so is reasoning and chain of
thought baked in training or is it just
prompt engineering that was accidentally
discovering these kind of capabilities
in larger models? And if so are there
other emergent behaviors besides our
reasoning and chain of thought that
you think might be discovered?
>> So uh
I mean it was not baked in by
by design it was it was basically
discovered as in like it was
I mean we gave it hard problems and then
we saw that it was basically by having
reasoning chains it was doing better. So
the GSM8K was the first paper that kind
of showed signs of life of this and then
with larger model like Palm we actually
saw that this was a very big deal and
one of the examples there was that it
could explain jokes that which was very
impressive and then from there the
reasoning models have emerged. So it was
not
but it has read all of the web so it's
it has definitely seen data which is
like more
methodical and systematic.
>> But the reasoning models are trained to
be reasoning more and more, right? So
it's they didn't it entire reasoning is
not an emergent behavior. The reasoning
models they're trained to be to be
thinking but like the models are
convergent so the models are going to be
trained such that they know when to they
need a lot of reasoning and when they
don't and and to generate the answers.
But chain of thought originally was an
emergent behavior. They noticed that oh,
if we
explain things the model, it's better.
>> of emergent behaviors in large models.
>> I don't think it's I would see it as
emergent behaviors per se, but I think
as I was mentioning, we're usually going
looking for certain things, right? So in
the agentic workflows, what we're
looking for is planning,
which is a form of reasoning. We're
looking for multi-step reasoning, which
we will cover in class as well. And then
we're looking for self-improvement or
self-correction. So all of these
capabilities would be nice to have in
like what gets the models there is a set
of questions that are worth like there
are papers on this kind of thing.
>> Like self-correction,
backtracking, things like that is like
yes, you could call it emergent, but you
could also say think about it that they
have seen this kind of behavior and it's
kind of like it's reinforced in the way
that they're fine-tuned. So it's
Yeah, it's hard to say.
Okay. Um so let's go through the the the
logistics for the class. Um here is a
list of all the amazing topics that
you're going to learn about. Um they are
um
yeah.
This is very cool. [laughter]
>> I think the main thing to remember here
is that the overall theme stays the same
and then we'll also have guest lectures
around from folks in Frontier AI Labs
and covering things all the way from say
how have has how has post-training
evolved or say even multimodal agents
and in robotics. So it's it's a it's
going to be a mix of lectures and guest
lectures and
and of course you have project
presentations.
>> So, here is some logistics that you all
know the the pre-record there. Just make
sure that you you are comfortable with
these pre-reqs as you
uh register then in the class. So, we
have the external website, but uh
make sure that you're
uh you check Canvas. That's where we
send out the latest updates at all
times.
Um and um
we will also upload the We try to upload
the lectures before we start every every
in every class so you have access to the
lectures.
Uh and we will also have We already have
the due dates for all the assignments
and all the projects, so you can check
it out.
Um
So, this quarter we're going to have
three homeworks. That's a difference
from between this class and that's one
of the differences. So, we have one more
amazing homework for you all that we've
designed and the TAs have done a great
job
and that's helps you
um hopefully learn
uh learn these topics better and more in
depth.
Um
And then we also have a course project.
So, the course project is where you can
kind of unleash your creativity and like
your your way of like building agentic
systems or going deeper into a question
uh and and designing experiments around
it and see what works and what doesn't.
Um we will provide some um kind of
examples or suggestions, but it could be
completely on you how to design this
project. We'll have some examples from
last year like the successful projects
from last year as well.
Uh it's going to be uploaded to
um Canvas or Actually, we'll display
them on the website.
>> Oh, on the website. Oh, cool.
>> Yeah. The public website, so you can all
see that. Um
So, yeah.
>> the course project, I think the main
thing to remember is that uh
we will have API credits and you can
work in teams of two to four people.
Right?
>> Yeah. Or
up to four, I
>> to four. Okay.
>> It can be one if you really want that.
We we we suggest you team up with
others.
Um at the very least, you have more
credits collectively, so you can run
more experiments. But then you might
also uh find a friend collaborator along
the way and you can um
um do something bigger. Um
and we are going to have this um
What is this? The course project. Yeah,
we're we're going to uh we're going to
let you know about some
uh some of the previous years and some
ideas that you can take. Um here are
some course project examples that are
acceptable. For example, a new
evaluation data set or a new benchmark.
Um you can design a project around the
reliability of a of an agentic agentic
system that already exists. You can take
a benchmark that exists and try to hill
climb on it with whatever idea great
idea that you have. Um and then or you
can just be You're going to have a whole
lot of papers covered in this course and
we have we are showing all of that to
you. They're all on the website. So as
you as we give these lectures, we kind
of expect you to also have read those
papers or read the papers along the way
and develop better and deeper intuitions
on how these methods work. And you your
project could always be improving those
or like questioning one of the decisions
that they have made and trying to uh
change that or uh or evaluate that. Um
Negative examples are like a survey
paper or like We just don't want We want
something researchy here. So we just
don't want like just an app that you put
together and you just show us something.
It has to be like Here is like, here is
the hypothesis.
Here is the question that we wanted to
answer. Here is the type of like
improvement we wanted to see or the type
of like properties we wanted to analyze
and then we have built that, right? We
want something something that
something more than live coding
basically in this.
>> Um I mean in terms of milestones, I
think that it's worthwhile to remember
that you want to start early.
So it's you need to have a project
proposal
somewhere around I think we we put it
early October.
>> Yeah.
>> And then uh
>> It's on the website, yeah.
>> It's on the website and then for the
midterm project presentation, we do want
you to have some progress. So 2 weeks
after the project proposal, we do expect
you to have like So start thinking about
like what experiments you want to run by
the time you get to the project proposal
so that
you actually go run them for the midterm
projects. And so we do expect you to
have made some progress in the midterm
project presentation. It should not just
be
here is a proposal and then the final
report has a lot of weight and then the
final poster presentation uh will be the
end of the quarter.
>> Um yes.
I
I think so. If you add to it, right?
>> See this one name I want to name it in
the past study, right?
Yeah, yeah, that's fine.
>> I I think it's
>> I mean as long as you're doing actual
work and it's not just like reusing the
work from
>> [laughter]
>> Um
>> We had We had students publishing papers
out of their projects
uh in the last quarter. So in the last
last time we taught the class. So that's
something you could it could be one of
you or many of you this time again
turning your research project, working
more on it and then
turning it into a publication and
conferences.
And so here is a save the date for for
our poster presentation. It's going to
be December 12th 4:00 to 6:00 p.m. So
we we would want you to be there and
present the posters. We'll have people
from industry joining and you can that's
where you can brag about what you've
done and just meet new people. Here is
the course grading rubric. So we have
three homeworks. That's 50% of your
of of your entire grade and then another
50% is on the project. And the duration
of these are kind of like a line with
how much how much the grading grading is
allocated to each of these. And we of
course expect you to honor
the honor code.
And let's see.
Office hours will be posted on Canvas.
You can ask your questions. We really
really encourage you to ask questions on
Ed Stem
and make it public so others probably if
you have a question
it's very likely others have the same
question. So please like do broadcast
this to everybody.
Ed Stem is
again you can ask questions and then
GradeScope is where you submit your
project milestones and everything else.
Yeah, the homeworks and everything.
We have the following late policy that
we think it's kind of like
between the generous kind of like
So, I I am generous side of things and
because the class is
big this quarter, we really can't make
any exceptions. So, try to use these
kind of late days wisely.
Uh
Audits are not allowed, but we will have
the the course
the we will have the videos videos on
YouTube eventually. Eventually.
And that's it. Any questions?
No?
All right.
>> Okay. Thanks everyone.